Guide to the John Arthur Wilkinson Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
John Arthur Wilkinson papers
1973-1983
MS 1661
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
6.5
(16 boxes)
The John Arthur Wilkinson Papers document the administrative and institutional history of the Center for Advocacy, Research and Planning (CARP), and offer a detailed view of the workings of a non-profit civil rights legal agency. CARP's work in the New Haven area with dozens of minority economic interests and neighborhood organizations is reflected in extensive correspondence, legal memoranda, proposals, and collected material. Much of the CARP material also addresses the general topic of African-Americans in the professions, particularly in law and business. There is substantive documentation on housing (discrimination, fair housing, neighborhood advocacy) and educational issues (especially concerning community and technical colleges).
Wilkinson, John Arthur, 1938-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of John A. Wilkinson, 1994.
Arrangement
The papers are arranged in three series: I. Administrative Files. II. Topical Files. III. Photographs.
Scope and Contents
The John Arthur Wilkinson Papers, donated by Wilkinson in 1994, consist of records which document the administrative and institutional history of the Center for Advocacy, Research and Planning and which offer a detailed view of the workings of a non-profit civil rights legal agency. The collection should prove useful for researchers interested in the history of civil rights and in the socio-economic affairs of minorities in New Haven. CARP's work with dozens of minority interest groups and neighborhood organizations is reflected in extensive correspondence, legal memoranda, proposals, and collected materials. Much of the CARP material also addresses the general topic of African-Americans in the professions, particularly in law and business. There is substantive documentation on housing (discrimination, fair housing, neighborhood advocacy) and educational issues (especially concerning community and technical colleges).
The papers range in date from 1973-1983. They are divided into three series: I. Administrative Files, II. Topical Files, and III. Photographs.
Both Series I and II are arranged alphabetically according to CARP's original office filing system.
Series I, ADMINISTRATIVE FILES, consists of documents pertaining to the administration of the organization. Files on the "Board of Directors," "Executive Director," "Funding Sources," and "Reports" comprise the majority of the series.
For those interested in the organizational history of CARP, the collected minutes and correspondence of the board of directors, contained within the "Meetings" files, offer an inside perspective, and span from 1973 to 1982. There is substantive information on CARP's working concerns: casework, funding, solicitation, personnel, organizational health, and budget. The minutes also offer important insight into CARP's founding and eventual demise.
Other documentation of CARP's case load and organizational life can be found in the "Reports" files and in the proposals to the New Haven Foundation and United Way, under "Funding Sources." The reports present in all of these files provide regular summaries of personnel and budgetary matters, pending cases, new clients, various events arranged or attended by CARP, and a (typically quarterly) financial statement. Other folders in "Funding Sources" include materials that document the extent of CARP's quest for outside monies. In particular, the correspondence with the Aetna Insurance Company and Southern New England Telephone reveals the complexity of the relationship between CARP and its corporate sponsors.
Fleming Norcott's final report as executive director provides a concise summary of CARP's activity through 1979. Other "Executive Director" files include some of the correspondence that flowed in and out of the CARP office from 1980 to 1982. It should be noted that the majority of CARP's correspondence (from 1973 to 1983), is scattered throughout the collection; correspondence with particular organizations/projects is often located in the organization/project file; and other correspondence is found in the "Meetings" files of the board of directors. "History" and "Publicity" files contain items which explain how CARP presented itself to the public and how CARP was regarded by the local media. Most of the cases and topics described in Series I can be explored in further detail in Series II.
Series II, TOPICAL FILES, documents CARP's working concerns, ranging from general issues like affirmative action to specific cases like the bid by the Silver Shields (an African American police organization) for fair treatment by the New Haven Police Department. In addition, there is considerable documentation on CARP's ongoing relationship with dozens of community groups, city and state commissions, and national membership organizations. CARP's standing as a significant player in the New Haven minority community is best represented in the substantial number of files on "Black Organizations," "Community Action Groups and Community Matters," and "New Haven Economics and Development." Among the materials on neighborhood organizations are extensive files on the Hill Central Community, the Newhallville Neighborhood Corporation, and the Dixwell/Newhallville Neighborhood Revitalization Program. There is material on several of CARP's major projects, including a proposed business/technical academy for the area (under "Education") and the organization of a minority economic development conference (under "New Haven Economics and Development"). For those interested in the concerns of African-American professionals, there are folders on the National Bar Association (a minority lawyers' organization), under "Bar associations and legal societies"; several files on individual professional organizations under "Black Organizations"; and folders on the Economic Development Conference, under "New Haven Economics and Development."
Evidence of CARP's presence in city and state politics can be found throughout Series II, particularly in such files as: "Commissions and Committees," "Community action groups and community matters," "Education," "Housing," and "New Haven Economics and Development." Under Clarance Jones in the early 1980s, CARP became increasingly involved in media concerns. CARP's participation on the WTNH-TV Minority Advisory Committee and its high profile response to a 1980 cross burning are documented in the "Media" files.
Series III, PHOTOGRAPHS, is comprised of one folder of 8x10 black and white photographic prints. They are undated and unidentified, but appear to be prints of CARP staff members and New Haven neighborhoods.
Biographical / Historical
JOHN WILKINSON AND THE CENTER FOR ADVOCACY, RESEARCH AND PLANNING
John Arthur Wilkinson was born in Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, on April 30, 1938, and received his B.A., M.A.T., and M.A. degrees from Yale University. Wilkinson was Assistant Dean of Yale College from 1961 to 1968, and was Associate Dean from 1968 to 1974. He served as headmaster of Hopkins School from 1974 to 1979. Wilkinson returned to Yale in 1979, serving as an Officer for Development until 1981, and as Secretary of the university from 1981 to 1987. From 1978 to 1983, Wilkinson served on the board of directors of the Center for Advocacy, Research and Planning (CARP), an organization founded in December 1973 as the legal arm and research agency of the Greater New Haven Chapter of the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP). CARP sought to represent the needs of minorities and the poor through traditional legal process. Separated from the NAACP for tax reasons in 1974, CARP continued to promote the concerns of disadvantaged people until it was disbanded in 1983.
CARP focused its activities on civil rights issues and did significant work in matters of affirmative action, fair housing, and community economic development. Under its first executive director, Fleming Norcott, CARP's docket included efforts on behalf of local African-American policemen in their bid for equal employment opportunities; litigative work to promote a New Haven location of South Central Community College (now Gateway Community-Technical College) and a regional technical vocational college; and representation of the Church Street South community whose housing was threatened by a proposed highway. During Norcott's six-year tenure, the non-profit CARP forged crucial relationships with and secured much of its funding from charitable organizations and corporate sponsors. CARP's board of directors assembled a diverse group of professionals from the New Haven and Yale communities.
In 1979, former Associate Director Clarance Jones assumed leadership, and in the 1980s, CARP produced several affirmative action plans, prepared studies on patients' rights and jury reform, and continued its investigation of the New Haven educational system. CARP also supported and worked with several minority businesses and economic development organizations in order to encourage economic opportunities in New Haven's minority community. Throughout its ten years, CARP maintained a strong presence in the community and in the local media. Lack of support funding, however, required the board of directors and Executive Director Joseph Searles to close the Center for Advocacy, Research and Planning in 1983.
Tenure of CARP Executive Directors
YEARS EXECUTIVE DIRECTOR
1973-1979 Fleming Norcott
1979-1982 Clarance Jones
1982-1983 Joseph Searles
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Affirmative action programs -- Connecticut; Affirmative action programs -- United States; African American lawyers; African Americans -- Civil rights; African Americans -- Employment; African Americans -- Housing; African Americans -- Connecticut; Civil rights; Community development; Community organization; Discrimination in employment; Housing; Minorities -- Housing; Minorities -- Political activity; Minority lawyers; Race discrimination -- Law and legislation; Technical education; Urban policy; Connecticut -- Social conditions; New Haven (Conn.) -- Civil rights; New Haven (Conn.) -- Social conditions; Jones, Clarance; Norcott, Fleming; Searles, Joseph; Wilkinson, John Arthur, 1938-; Center for Advocacy, Research and Planning (New Haven, Conn.); National Association for the Advancement of Colored People. New Haven Branch
- ADMINISTRATIVE FILES, Series I
  - Background, 1974, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Board of Directors
    - General, 1974-1979 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Committees
      - Fund raising committee, 1976, 1980-1982 (Box 1, Folder 3-4)
      - Nominating committee, 1980-1982 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Personnel committee, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 6)
        General note
        See also: box 8, folder 190-195
      - Program development committee, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Public relations committee, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Human rights award, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Meetings
      - 1973-1975 (Box 1, Folder 10-37)
      - 1976-1978 (Box 2, Folder 38-67)
      - 1979-1981 (Box 3, Folder 68-89)
      - 1982-1983 (Box 4, Folder 90-98)
  - Budget/financial
    - Audits, 1978-1981 (Box 4, Folder 99-102)
    - Financial information, 1975, 1977-1978, 1980-1981 (Box 4, Folder 103-105)
  - By-laws, 1975-1978, undated (Box 4, Folder 106)
  - CARP (Center for Advocacy, Research and Planning) vs. CARP (Collegiate Association for the Research of Principles of Connecticut, Inc.), 1977-1981 (Box 4, Folder 107)
  - Client intake sheets, 1980-1981 (Box 4, Folder 108)
  - Executive Director
    - Norcott, Fleming: Final report, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 109)
    - Jones, Clarance
      - Correspondence, 1980-1981 (Box 4, Folder 110-127)
      - Correspondence, 1981-1982 (Box 5, Folder 128-137)
    - Interim: correspondence, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 138-139)
    - Searles, Joseph
      - Correspondence, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 140-146)
      - Speeches and statements, 1982, undated (Box 5, Folder 147)
  - Funding Sources
    - Corporations
      - General, 1974-1981 (Box 5, Folder 148-149)
      - Aetna Insurance Company, 1976-1982 (Box 5, Folder 150-151)
        See also: box 13, folder 304-306
      - Carnegie Corporation, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 152)
      - Pratt and Whitney Aircraft Group, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 153)
      - Southern New England Telephone, 1980-1981 (Box 5, Folder 154-155)
    - Foundations
      - Field Foundation, 1981 (Box 6, Folder 156)
      - Hazen Foundation, 1974-1982 (Box 6, Folder 157)
      - New Haven Foundation, 1973-1983 (Box 6, Folder 158-174)
    - Housing and Urban Development grant, 1979 (Box 6, Folder 175)
    - Letters of support, 1980-1981 (Box 6, Folder 176)
    - Reasons for funding, undated (Box 7, Folder 177)
    - United Way, 1977-1982 undated (Box 7, Folder 178-184)
  - History [includes histories and brochure], 1974-1980 (Box 7, Folder 185)
  - Interoffice memoranda, 1982-1983 (Box 7, Folder 186)
  - Litigation models, 1977 (Box 7, Folder 187)
  - Location [office], 1975-1982 (Box 7, Folder 188)
  - Mailing lists, undated (Box 7, Folder 189)
  - Personnel
    See also: box 1, folder 6
    - In-school work experience program, 1982 (Box 8, Folder 190)
    - Job descriptions, 1976-1981 (Box 8, Folder 191)
    - Policies, 1974-1980 (Box 8, Folder 192)
    - Student employment applications, 1981 (Box 8, Folder 193)
    - Volunteer action center, 1982 (Box 8, Folder 194)
    - Yale and Bridgeport workstudy, 1981-1982 (Box 8, Folder 195)
  - Publicity
    - Newspaper articles, 1974-1980 (Box 8, Folder 196-197)
    - Press releases, 1980 (Box 8, Folder 199)
    - Public relations, 1980 (Box 8, Folder 198)
  - Registration and incorporation, 1974-1981 (Box 8, Folder 200)
  - Reports
    - 1974-1975 (Box 8, Folder 201-208)
    - 1976-1982 (Box 9, Folder 209-233)
  - Tax exemption
    - Federal, 1974-1975 (Box 9, Folder 234)
    - State, 1974-1982 (Box 9, Folder 235)
- TOPICAL FILES, Series II
  - Affirmative Action
    - General, 1975-1980 (Box 10, Folder 236)
    - Anti-redlining plan, 1975 (Box 10, Folder 237)
      General
      See also: box 15, folders 321-322
    - Board of Education, 1979-1981 (Box 10, Folder 238)
    - Construction contracts, 1974-1978 (Box 10, Folder 239)
    - Fair housing marketing, 1975 (Box 10, Folder 240)
      See also: Box 14, folder 316
  - Bar associations and legal societies
    - Connecticut Bar Association, 1974-1979 (Box 10, Folder 241)
    - Connecticut Bar Examination Committee, 1974-1981 (Box 10, Folder 242)
    - National Bar Association, 1978-1979 (Box 10, Folder 243)
    - National Lawyers Guild, 1979 (Box 10, Folder 244)
    - New Haven City Bar Association, 1975-1979 (Box 10, Folder 245)
    - Others, 1979, undated (Box 10, Folder 246)
  - Black Organizations
    See also: box 12, folder 275-300
    - Afro-American Cultural Center, undated (Box 10, Folder 247)
    - Afro-American Historical Society, 1981 (Box 10, Folder 248)
    - Black Coalition of New Haven, Inc., 1977-1978 (Box 10, Folder 249)
    - Black judges in Connecticut, 1979 (Box 10, Folder 250)
    - Black lawyers in Connecticut, 1973-1980 (Box 10, Folder 251)
    - Black Management Association of Southern New England Telephone, 1978-1980 (Box 10, Folder 252)
    - Greater Hartford Black Law Society, 1978 (Box 10, Folder 253)
  - Block grants, 1981 (Box 10, Folder 254)
  - Commissions and Committees
    - Charter Revision Committee [City of New Haven], 1981 (Box 10, Folder 255)
    - Civil Rights Coordinating Committee, 1979-1982 (Box 10, Folder 256)
    - Connecticut Civil Liberties Union, 1978-1980, undated (Box 11, Folder 257-259)
    - Connecticut Commission on Human Rights and Opportunities, 1977-1981 (Box 11, Folder 260-265)
    - Equal Employment Opportunity Commission, 1978-1979 (Box 11, Folder 266)
    - Juvenile Justice Advisory Committee, 1981 (Box 11, Folder 267)
    - Purchasing Advisory Committee [City of New Haven], 1979-1982, undated (Box 12, Folder 268-273)
    - U.S. Commission on Human Rights, 1979-1980 (Box 12, Folder 274)
  - Community Action Groups and Community Matters
    See also: box 14, folder 314-323 box 16, folder 333-342
    - Anti-Hunger Coalition, 1980 (Box 12, Folder 275)
    - Citizens for Humanizing Criminal Justice, 1979 (Box 12, Folder 276)
    - Comprehensive Employment and Training Administration (CETA), 1978 (Box 12, Folder 277)
    - Church Street South, 1981-1982 (Box 12, Folder 278)
    - Coalition for an Equitable Region, 1979-1980 (Box 12, Folder 279)
    - Connecticut Association for Human Services, 1978 (Box 12, Folder 280)
    - Connecticut Black Caucus, 1981 (Box 12, Folder 281)
    - Co-op Housing Technical Advisory Group, 1982 (Box 12, Folder 282)
    - Hill Central Community, Inc., 1981 (Box 12, Folder 283)
    - International Association of Human Rights Agencies, 1981 (Box 12, Folder 284)
    - Lighthouse Park, 1981 (Box 12, Folder 285)
    - National Association for the Advancement of Colored People, New Haven, 1979-1981 (Box 12, Folder 286)
    - Narcotics Addiction Research and Community Opportunities, Inc. (NARCO), 1977-1979 (Box 13, Folder 287)
    - Neighborhood Assistance Project, 1982 (Box 13, Folder 288)
    - New Haven Coalition for People, 1982-1983 (Box 13, Folder 289)
    - New Haven Housing Coalition, 1980-1981 (Box 13, Folder 290)
    - New Haven Legal Association, Inc., 1977-1978 (Box 13, Folder 291)
    - New Haven Volunteers, 1978-1979 (Box 13, Folder 292)
    - New Haven Youth Association, 1980 (Box 13, Folder 293)
    - Newhallville Neighborhood Corporation, 1982-1983 (Box 13, Folder 294)
      See also: box 16, folder 336
    - People Acting for Change, 1978 (Box 13, Folder 295)
    - Rt. 34 Air Rights Garage, 1982 (Box 13, Folder 296)
    - Save Our Schools, 1981 (Box 13, Folder 297)
    - Silver Shields, 1981, undated (Box 13, Folder 298)
    - Town-gown relations, 1981 (Box 13, Folder 299)
    - Urban League, 1978-1979 (Box 13, Folder 300)
  - Conferences, 1978-1981 (Box 13, Folder 301)
  - Discrimination
    - Banking, undated (Box 13, Folder 302)
    - Equal Employment Opportunities Commission, 1981 (Box 13, Folder 303)
  - Education
    See also: box 10, folder 238
    - Business Industrial Skills Agency, 1980-1982 (Box 13, Folder 304-306)
      See also: box 5, folders 150-151
    - Mayor's Education Management Task Force, 1981 (Box 14, Folder 307-308)
    - Regional Council on Education for Employment, 1982 (Box 14, Folder 309)
    - South Central Community College [now Gateway Community-Technical College], 1972-1976, 1979-1982, undated (Box 14, Folder 310-312)
    - Technical college proposal, 1975 (Box 14, Folder 313)
  - Housing
    - Census '80 True Count Committee, 1980 (Box 14, Folder 314)
    - Clippings, 1979-1982 (Box 14, Folder 315)
    - Fair housing, New Haven, 1977-1982 (Box 14, Folder 316)
      See also: box 10, folder 240
    - Morris Cove, 1975-1978 (Box 14, Folder 317)
    - New Haven Housing Coalition, 1980-1982 (Box 14, Folder 318)
    - Public housing siting, 1981 (Box 14, Folder 319)
    - Public housing suit, 1980-1981 (Box 15, Folder 320)
    - Redlining [mortgage and insurance], 1980-1981 (Box 15, Folder 321-322)
      See also: box 10, folder 237
    - Tenant representation, 1972-1978 (Box 15, Folder 323)
  - Ku Klux Klan, 1980-1981, undated (Box 15, Folder 324-325)
    See also: box 16, folder 331
  - Labor: Connecticut Labor Department, 1979 (Box 15, Folder 326)
  - Legal memoranda and student legal memoranda, 1980-1981 (Box 15, Folder 327-328)
  - Media
    - Federal Communications Commission license challenges, 1976-1978, undated (Box 15, Folder 329)
    - Racial bias in newspapers, 1981-1982 (Box 16, Folder 330)
    - Television response to 1980 cross burning (Box 16, Folder 331)
      See also: box 15, folders 324-325
    - WTNH Minority Advisory Committee, 1981-1982 (Box 16, Folder 332)
  - New Haven Economics and Development
    See also: box 10, folders 247-253
    - Chase and Rouse Company, 1981 (Box 16, Folder 333)
    - Community development, 1978, undated (Box 16, Folder 334)
    - Community Development Act, 1973-1981 (Box 16, Folder 335)
    - Dixwell/Newhallville Neighborhood Revitalization Program, 1979, 1981 (Box 16, Folder 336)
      See also: box 13, folder 294
    - Economic development conference, 1979 (Box 16, Folder 337)
    - Greater New Haven Business and Professional Association, 1981-1982 (Box 16, Folder 338)
    - Halcyon report and summary, undated (Box 16, Folder 339)
    - Heritage Hall Development Corporation, 1981 (Box 16, Folder 340)
    - Hilgenhurst report excerpts, undated (Box 16, Folder 341)
    - Minority Small Business Investment Company (MESBIC) Advisory Board, 1981 (Box 16, Folder 342)
  - Reapportionment, 1980-1982 (Box 16, Folder 343-344)
  - Transportation, 1979 (Box 16, Folder 345)
- PHOTOGRAPHS, Series III
  - Photographs, undated (Box 16, Folder 346)